<oai_qdc:qualifieddc xmlns:oai_qdc="http://worldcat.org/xmlschemas/qdc-1.0/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://worldcat.org/xmlschemas/qdc-1.0/ http://worldcat.org/xmlschemas/qdc/1.0/qdc-1.0.xsd http://purl.org/net/oclcterms http://worldcat.org/xmlschemas/oclcterms/1.4/oclcterms-1.4.xsd">
    <dc:title>Safe</dc:title>
    <dc:description>A Philadelphia newspaper revels in the passage of the 19th Amendment, which gave women the right to vote. Here, the Lady sits safely atop the Constitution while an anti-suffragist rat shakes its fist.</dc:description>
    <dc:description>The 19th Amendment to the U. S. Constitution granted women the right to vote. When the Tennessee General Assembly passed the ratification resolution on August 18, 1920, it gave the amendment the 36th and final state necessary for ratification. Suffragists and anti-suffragists lobbied furiously to secure votes during that intense summer in Nashville. The ratification resolution passed easily in the Tennessee State Senate on August 13, but the House of Representatives was deadlocked. When young Harry T. Burn of Niota changed his vote to support ratification of the 19th Amendment, he broke a tie in the House of Representatives and made history. Josephine A. Pearson (1868-1944) was an educator from Monteagle who became president of the Tennessee State Association Opposed to Woman Suffrage and the Southern Woman’s League for the Rejection of the Susan B. Anthony Amendment. She worked tirelessly with various women&#x27;s groups, religious and political leaders throughout Tennessee in an unsuccessful effort to prevent the passage of women’s suffrage.</dc:description>
    <dc:date>1920 August 27</dc:date>
    <dc:coverage>Philadelphia (Pa.)</dc:coverage>
    <dc:publisher>Evening Public Ledger</dc:publisher>
    <dc:coverage>Philadelphia (Pa.)</dc:coverage>
    <dc:source>Carrie Chapman Catt Papers, 1916-1921</dc:source>
    <dcterms:instructionalMethod>5.46; US.18; Women&#x27;s Suffrage and the 19th Amendment; Progressive Era</dcterms:instructionalMethod>
    <dc:subject>Women -- Suffrage -- Tennessee; Constitutional amendments -- United States -- Ratification; Women -- Caricatures and cartoons</dc:subject>
    <dc:subject>Political cartoons; Press; Women&#x27;s rights; Women&#x27;s suffrage</dc:subject>
    <dcterms:isPartOf>72-119</dcterms:isPartOf>
    <dc:source>Tennessee State Library and Archives</dc:source>
    <dc:identifier>33890</dc:identifier>
    <dc:source>I-J-2, Box 4, Folder 4</dc:source>
    <dc:type>Still Image; Text</dc:type>
    <dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
    <dcterms:medium>Political cartoons</dcterms:medium>
    <dcterms:isVersionOf>1077</dcterms:isVersionOf>
    <dcterms:references>http://sos.tn.gov/products/tsla/catt-carrie-chapman-papers-1916-1921</dcterms:references>
    <dc:rights> 	While TSLA houses an item, it does not necessarily hold the copyright on the item, nor may it be able to determine if the item is still protected under current copyright law. Users are solely responsible for determining the existence of such instances and for obtaining any other permissions and paying associated fees that may be necessary for the intended use. </dc:rights>
    <dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/p15138coll27/id/0</dc:identifier>
</oai_qdc:qualifieddc>