<oai_qdc:qualifieddc xmlns:oai_qdc="http://worldcat.org/xmlschemas/qdc-1.0/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://worldcat.org/xmlschemas/qdc-1.0/ http://worldcat.org/xmlschemas/qdc/1.0/qdc-1.0.xsd http://purl.org/net/oclcterms http://worldcat.org/xmlschemas/oclcterms/1.4/oclcterms-1.4.xsd">
    <dc:title>Selected profane and sacred images</dc:title>
    <dc:description>The front plate of William Strickland&#x27;s European architectural sketchbook.  The sketch shows a watercolor drawing of a vine-covered monument with a Latin inscription. The translation reads: &quot;Selected profane and sacred images of Britain and Roman antiquities, suspension bridges; bridges that are modern and bridges in ruins, up to the Trivoli Aqueduct completed in the name of Pope Gregory the Great. Peace be to you.&quot;</dc:description>
    <dc:description>The sketchbook details sketches made by Strickland during a visit to Europe in 1838.  After several lucrative commissions, he took his wife and two daughters, Emily and Jane, to Europe.  It was an opportune time to go as there were few prospects of obtaining new work.  Because of a financial panic and accompanying labor unrest, no one had the finances or inclination for civil building.  Except for a few Federal commissions, Strickland remained idle for the next several years.  In January 1838, he and his family sailed from Philadelphia for Liverpool, England, and remained abroad for about six months.</dc:description>
    <dc:date>1838</dc:date>
    <dc:creator>Strickland, William, 1787-1854</dc:creator>
    <dc:source>William Strickland Sketchbook, 1838</dc:source>
    <dc:subject>Monuments &amp; memorials; Sculpture; Antiquities; Watercolors; Sketches; Sketchbooks</dc:subject>
    <dcterms:isPartOf>2005-014</dcterms:isPartOf>
    <dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
    <dc:identifier>32924</dc:identifier>
    <dc:type>Still Image</dc:type>
    <dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
    <dc:language>no linguistic content.</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>While TSLA houses an item, it does not necessarily hold the copyright on the item, nor may it be able to determine if the item is still protected under current copyright law.  Users are solely responsible for determining the existence of such instances and for obtaining any other permissions and paying associated fees that may be necessary for the intended use.</dc:rights>
    <dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/Strickland/id/37</dc:identifier>
</oai_qdc:qualifieddc>