<repository xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/"      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instanc">
<record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/0</identifier><datestamp>2012-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/1</identifier><datestamp>2012-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/2</identifier><datestamp>2012-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/3</identifier><datestamp>2012-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/4</identifier><datestamp>2012-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/5</identifier><datestamp>2012-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/6</identifier><datestamp>2012-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/7</identifier><datestamp>2012-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/8</identifier><datestamp>2012-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/9</identifier><datestamp>2012-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/10</identifier><datestamp>2012-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/11</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-10</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/12</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-10</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/13</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-10</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/14</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-10</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/15</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-10</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/16</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-10</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/17</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-10</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/18</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-10</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/19</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-10</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/20</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-08</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/21</identifier><datestamp>2012-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/22</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>An Act for the Establishment of Washington College</dc:title>
<dc:description>An Act for the Establishment of Washington College 
An act for the establishment of Washington College in honor to the illustrious President of the United States at Salem in Washington county. 
Whereas the Legislature of North Carolina, established the academy in Washington county, by the name of Martin academy, which has continued for ten or twelve years past under the presidency of the reverend Samuel Douk, and has been of considerable utility to the public, and affords a prospect of future usefulness if invested with powers and privileges appertaining to Colleges: 
Sec 1. Be it enacted by the Governor, Legislative Council, and House of Representatives of the Territory of the United States of America south of the river Ohio, That the reverend Samuel Doak president, the reverend Charles Cummins, Edward Crawford, John Coson, James Balch, Robert Henderson and Gideon Blackburn, Judge Joseph Anderson, General John Sevier, Colonels Landon Carter and Daniel Kenedy, Majors Leeroy Taylor and John Sevier, John Tipton, William Cocke, Archibald</dc:description>
<dc:description>&quot;An act for the establishment of Washington College in honor to the Illustrious President of the United States at Salem in Washington County.&quot; The act is handwritten and is five pages in length.  The resolution passed at Knoxville on July 10, 1795.  It is signed by Governor William Blount. 
 The act renaming re-naming St. Martin’s Academy to Washington College in honor of President George Washington was one of the varied acts passed by the Southwest Territory General Assembly. Samuel Doak (1749-1830), a Virginia Presbyterian minister and pioneer, assumed his first pastorate in Abingdon, Virginia, and also began to &quot;ride circuit&quot; in eastern Tennessee. In 1778 he settled in Tennessee in Sullivan County and was ordained a minister. In 1780 he moved to Washington County, where he formed Salem Church and a school, which was chartered as St. Martin's Academy in 1783, the first chartered school in the region. In 1795 it became Washington College. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33669_Intro.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Knoxville (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1795 July 10</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Territory of the United States, South of the River Ohio. General Assembly</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Tennessee. General Assembly. Acts, Public and Private, 1790-[ongoing]</dc:source>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>RG 260</dc:relation>
<dc:description>On May 26, 1790, President George Washington signed into law an act of Congress passed earlier in the month that established the Territory of the United States South of the River Ohio (Southwest Territory). Embracing the western lands ceded by the state of North Carolina on December 22, 1789, the new territory was to be governed under the terms of the Ordinance of 1787, which created its predecessor, the Northwest Territory. This act passed on July 5, 1795, renamed St. Martin’s Academy, located in Washington County, to Washington College in honor of President George Washington. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33669_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library and Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33669</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Universities &amp; colleges</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Doak, Samuel, 1749-1830; Washington College (Washington County, Tenn.); Washington County (Tenn.); Washington, George, 1732-1799; Sevier, John, 1745-1815; Carter, Landon, 1760-1800; Cocke, William, 1747-1828; Roane, Archiibald, 1759-1819</dc:subject>
<dc:relation>RG 260</dc:relation>
<dc:rights>While TSLA houses an item, it does not necessarily hold the copyright on the item, nor may it be able to determine if the item is still protected under current copyright law. Users are solely responsible for determining the existence of such instances and for obtaining any other permissions and paying associated fees that may be necessary for the intended use.</dc:rights>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/22</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/23</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>States of America</dc:title>
<dc:description>This color map reflects twenty &quot;States of America.&quot; Though each of the twenty states is marked with a Roman numeral, the map actually reflects an earlier period in the nation's history with its labelling of  territories, Indian tribes, and East Tennessee as &quot;Franklinia.&quot;  Denoted on the map are cities and towns; rivers and major waterways; and Indian tribal locations.  The map reaches north into Canada, south to the Gulf of Mexico, east to the North Atlantic Ocean, and west to Louisiana.</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>United States</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1840</dc:date>
<dc:source>TSLA Map Collection</dc:source>
<dc:type>Map</dc:type>
<dc:relation>MAP 2452</dc:relation>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33670</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Maps; Statehood; Cities &amp; towns; Rivers; Bodies of water; Indian encampments</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>United States -- Maps; Franklin (State) -- Maps; Indians of North America -- Maps</dc:subject>
<dc:publisher>Fisher, Son, &amp; Co.</dc:publisher>
<dc:rights>While TSLA houses an item, it does not necessarily hold the copyright on the item, nor may it be able to determine if the item is still protected under current copyright law. Users are solely responsible for determining the existence of such instances and for obtaining any other permissions and paying associated fees that may be necessary for the intended use.</dc:rights>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/23</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/24</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>Letter to Governor Sevier from William Blount and William Cocke</dc:title>
<dc:description>Facsimile letter to Governor John Sevier from Representatives William Blount and William Cocke giving the status of Tennessee's admission as a state.  The letter explains problems encountered during the admission process, such as political factions. As a result, Tennessee's electors were reduced from four to three.</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Philadelphia (Pa.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1796 June 2</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Blount, William, 1749-1800</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Governor John Sevier Papers, 1796-1801</dc:source>
<dc:source>Correspondence</dc:source>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>GP 2</dc:relation>
<dc:description>Often called the &quot;Father of Tennessee, John Sevier was born in Virginia in 1745, he eventually moved to Washington County, TN and became Tennessee's first governor. He became a hero after he led an army of settlers at the Battle of Kings Mountain.</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33676</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Politics &amp; government</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Cocke, William, 1747-1801; Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1775-1865; Sevier, John, 1745-1815</dc:subject>
<dc:relation>GP 2</dc:relation>
<dc:relation>http://www.tennessee.gov/tsla/history/govpapers/findingaids/gp2.pdf</dc:relation>
<dc:rights>While TSLA houses an item, it does not necessarily hold the copyright on the item, nor may it be able to determine if the item is still protected under current copyright law. Users are solely responsible for determining the existence of such instances and for obtaining any other permissions and paying associated fees that may be necessary for the intended use.</dc:rights>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/24</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/25</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>Circular to the members of the General Assembly</dc:title>
<dc:description>Circular to members of the General Assembly. 
Knoxville 4th July 1796. 
Sir 
I have received information from the Honorable Messrs. Blount and Cocke; That Tennessee is by and act of Congress admitted as a member State of the Union. 
By this act we are only entitled to the privilege of having one Representative; The Senate of the United States objected against our Senators taking seats within their body. 
Matters being thus deranged, it becomes expedient and necessary, for the Assembly to be convened at an early day, in order to alter and regulate our present mode of election for Representatives, Electors of President and Vice President of the United States, reelect Senators and other business of Public utility. 
Your punctual attendance at the seat of Government, on the last saturday in the present month will be expected. 
I have the honor to be respectfully 
Your most obedient humble servant 
(signed)</dc:description>
<dc:description>Governor John Sevier's address to the Tennessee General Assembly as transcribed by Daniel Smith.  Sevier debriefs members about the outcome of Tennessee's appeal for admission.  At this time, he also summons the members to attend the first session of the General Assembly.</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Knoxville (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1796 July 4</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Smith, Daniel, 1748-1818</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Governor John Sevier Papers, 1796-1801</dc:source>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>GP 2</dc:relation>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33677</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Politics &amp; government</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Smith, Daniel, 1748-1818; Tennessee. General Assembly; Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1775-1865</dc:subject>
<dc:relation>GP 2</dc:relation>
<dc:relation>http://www.tennessee.gov/tsla/history/govpapers/findingaids/gp2.pdf</dc:relation>
<dc:rights>While TSLA houses an item, it does not necessarily hold the copyright on the item, nor may it be able to determine if the item is still protected under current copyright law. Users are solely responsible for determining the existence of such instances and for obtaining any other permissions and paying associated fees that may be necessary for the intended use.</dc:rights>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/25</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/41</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>Donelson Journal</dc:title>
<dc:description>Journal documenting the 1779-1780 river voyage of Col. John Donelson and others, including women, children, and African Americans. The travelers sought to establish the first permanent settlement west of the Appalachians. Handwritten in ink on paper.  The Donelson Journal has long been of special interest to those who study Tennessee history, as it purports to be a firsthand account of a planned river journey to found the first permanent settlement to the west of the Appalachians - 200 miles further west than previous settlements. The authenticity of the journal has recently been called into question, and may actually have been written long after the actual trip to Nashville. The document proclaims to be the “Journal of a voyage intended by God’s permission in the good boat Adventure from Fort Patrick Henry on Holston River to the French Salt Springs on Cumberland River, kept by John DONELSON,” but a recent article in the Tennessee Historical Quarterly by Paul Clements argues that it is much more likely that the journal was written by Donelson’s son. 
The journey down the river was dangerous and involved tense encounters with Native Americans, physical dangers, inclement weather, and other hazards. Numerous casualties occurred during the journey, including the death of a young baby that was lost overboard during an altercation with Native Americans. Food was scarce, but the group survived by hunting animals, usually buffalo, and on one occasion, a swan, which was deemed “very delicious.” The travelers frequently interacted with Native Americans, some of whom were friendly and others who were hostile. They even worked with a so-called “half-breed” (part Indian, part white) named Archy Coody who guided them (and led them into an ambush) during a portion of their journey. The best scholarly interpretation of their journey was written in 1960 by Harriette Simpson Arnow in her book Seedtime on the Cumberland. In it she considers the inexperienced leadership of Donelson and Robertson and the many misfortunes that befell them during the trip. Arnow asserts that those who made the trip overland at the same time “actually did the hard and ugly work” of establishing a permanent settlement in Middle Tennessee, although the story of the dramatic river journey has long captured the imagination of those who have come across the Donelson Journal. 

</dc:description>
<dc:date>1779-1780?</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Donelson, John, 1755-1830</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Tennessee Historical Society Miscellaneous Files, 1688-1951</dc:source>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>THS 195</dc:relation>
<dc:description>This journal documents the 1779-1780 river voyage of Col. John Donelson and others, including women, children, and African Americans. The travelers were seeking to establish the first permanent settlement to the west of the Appalachians - 200 miles further west than previous settlements. On December 22, 1779, Col. John Donelson’s group departed on the boat Adventure from Fort Patrick Henry on the Holston River. After many harrowing adventures and considerable suffering, they arrived at French Lick, which is now Nashville, Tennessee. Donelson’s crew included many family members of the men who took a different route west with James Robertson. This group joined Donelson’s flotilla at the mouth of the Clinch River, and was led by Capt. John Blackmore. Upon arriving at the French Lick and joining Robertson’s group, a forted station was constructed next to the Cumberland River. The successful completion of this voyage in April 1780 culminated in the founding of the settlement of Nashborough (later Nashville).  The document purports to be a firsthand account of this journey, but the authenticity of the item has recently been called into question. Although the diary prominently displays the words, “the original” on the front, it is possible that the author of the journal is not John Donelson himself, but rather, his son, John Donelson, Jr. A detailed investigation of this possibility can be found in: Paul Clements, “Tennessee Notes: An Analysis of ‘The Original’ Donelson Journal and Associated Accounts of the Donelson Party Voyage.” Tennessee Historical Quarterly 64, no. 4 (Winter 2005): 338-349. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33635_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee Historical Society</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33635</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Documents; Discovery &amp; exploration; Westward movement; Frontier &amp; pioneer life; Rivers; Indigenous peoples</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Tennessee -- History -- To 1865; African Americans; Indians of North America; Donelson, John, 1755-1830 -- Diaries</dc:subject>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/41</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/48</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>Tennessee Constitution, 1834</dc:title>
<dc:description>This first revision of the Tennessee Constitution addressed a variety of problems present in the original 1796 Constitution. Pages are handwritten on oversize paper and are laminated.  In the period between 1796 and 1834, the population of Tennessee grew at large percentage. In 1800, Tennessee’s population was 105,602, and by 1830, the population had grown to 681,904. By 1830, Tennessee could no longer be considered the frontier. Tennessee had an urban population of over 5,000. The Constitution that governed those first Tennesseans, a few thousand rural settlers, was now becoming stressed trying to govern a population reaching nearly 700,000. Read more at www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33662_Intro.pdf
</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Nashville (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1834</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Tennessee. General Assembly</dc:creator>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:description>In the first half of the nineteenth century a number of states, responding to social forces pressing the case for a greater role for the average white citizen, revised their constitutions. Tennessee became part of this trend when, on May 19, 1834, sixty delegates assembled in Nashville in a constitutional convention and selected William Carter of Carter County as president of the proceedings. The principal interests of the delegates concerned the provisions of the 1796 constitution dealing with taxation and representation. White citizens received greater opportunities for political expression and office holding. However, the newfound concern with the &quot;common man&quot; extended to whites only. In making suffrage changes, the delegates restricted the vote to white men, thereby disfranchising free black males, who had voted under the 1796 Constitution. A variety of other issues were addressed. Antislavery groups petitioned for the abolition of slavery, but the delegates rejected their appeals. Instead, the convention added language requiring the approval of slave owners for the passage of any future acts of emancipation. When presented to the voters in March 1835, the new constitution was ratified by a vote of 42,666 in favor to 17,691 against. Read more at http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33662_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33662</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>State government; Constitutions; Constitutional conventions; Law &amp; legal affairs; Slavery; Freedmen; Suffrage; Lotteries</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Tennessee. General Assembly; Carroll, William, 1788-1844</dc:subject>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/48</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/90</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>Tennessee Constitution, 1796</dc:title>
<dc:description>Tennessee's first constitution, adopted in 1796. Handwritten in ink on paper.  The 1796 Tennessee Constitution was drafted in Knoxville over a four week period by a convention of fifty-five delegates (two delegates from each of the territory’s eleven counties).  These delegates included William Blount (president of the convention), James Robertson, William Cocke, and Andrew Jackson.  Although John Sevier did not participate directly in the proceedings, he did work behind the scenes to promote Blount’s position.  The convention delegates never intended to present the Constitution to the citizens for ratification.  Instead, the delegates hurried to finish the Constitution in order to present a copy to Congress before their spring adjournment.  After much contention, a compromise was reached giving Tennessee immediate statehood on the condition of having only one representative in the House.  The bill was signed by President Washington on June 1, 1796.

The 1796 Constitution’s declarations on rights, taxation, and legislative authority were drawn largely from the North Carolina and Pennsylvania constitutions.  The Declaration of Rights and the position on suffrage differentiate Tennessee’s constitution from others of its time.  According to historian J.G.M. Ramsey, Thomas Jefferson described Tennessee’s as the “least imperfect and most republican of the state constitutions.”  Article III, Section 1st gives all freemen (white and black) twenty-one years of age who owned a freehold or who had resided in the county six months the right to vote.  There was also a provision giving men serving in the militia the right to elect their officers. </dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Knoxville (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1796 February 6</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Tennessee. Constitutional Convention (1796)</dc:creator>
<dc:type>StillImage</dc:type>
<dc:description>http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33633_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library and Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33633</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Constitutions</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Tennessee -- History -- To 1865</dc:subject>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/90</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/95</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>Act for the Purpose of Raising a Fund for Erecting a District Jail and Stocks in the Town of Nashville in the Mero District</dc:title>
<dc:description>The document is a four page, unnumbered handwritten document found in &quot;Acts of the Southwest Territory.&quot; It is dated September 27, 1794 and signed by Governor William Blount and Secretary David Wilson.  On May 26, 1790, President George Washington signed into law an act of Congress passed earlier in the month that established the Territory of the United States South of the River Ohio (Southwest Territory). Embracing the western lands ceded by the state of North Carolina on December 22, 1789, the new territory was to be governed under the terms of the Ordinance of 1787, which created its predecessor, the Northwest Territory.
www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33667_Intro.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Knoxville (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1794 September 27</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Territory of the United States, South of the River Ohio. General Assembly</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Tennessee. General Assembly. Acts, Public and Private, 1790-[ongoing]</dc:source>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>RG 260</dc:relation>
<dc:description>On May 26, 1790, President George Washington signed into law an act of Congress passed earlier in the month that established the Territory of the United States South of the River Ohio (Southwest Territory). Embracing the western lands ceded by the state of North Carolina on December 22, 1789, the new territory was to be governed under the terms of the Ordinance of 1787, which created its predecessor, the Northwest Territory. This act passed on September 27, 1794, created a lottery to raise the funs needed to build a district jail and stocks in the town of Nashville. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33667_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33667</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Jails; Stocks (Punishment); Punishment devices; Punishment &amp; torture; Lotteries</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Nashville (Tenn.); Blount, William, 1749-1800</dc:subject>
<dc:relation>RG 260</dc:relation>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/95</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/101</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>Watauga Purchase (Old Book A)</dc:title>
<dc:description>This volume comprises the first land grant book created for the area which became Tennessee.  Located at the front is the contract or treaty formalizing the land purchase between the Watauga Association and the Cherokee chiefs.  It is followed by the entry of the Watauga grants (generally individual tracts of 200-400 acres).  The remainder contains recorded Washington County grants issued by the State of North Carolina.  In the years prior to the American Revolution, settlers primarily from Virginia filtered down the Holston Valley to inhabit the fertile areas along the Watauga and Holston Rivers.  As Wataugans went about the business of settling their families, developing their lands, and co-existing with the Cherokees, they sowed the initial seeds of democracy and self-governance in the West and, specifically, the land that was to be Tennessee.

The Watauga settlers who gained a foothold in the area around 1769 occupied a tenuous position.  King George’s Proclamation of 1763 forbade settlement west of the Appalachian divide, and though it could be argued that two later treaties with the Cherokee nullified this order, the Wataugans’ status might still be considered that of squatter.  In addition, the Watauga inhabitants feared their settlement would become a haven for debtors and criminals.  Moses Fisk, a nineteenth-century historian, described them “as little protected, controlled, or recollected by any government whatever, as their co-tenants the bears.”  The order, justice, and security that a form of government would provide proved enticing.

Their rationale in place, and with John Carter as their chairman, the Wataugans formed the Watauga Association in May of 1772.  Though their actions may have been considered a temporary emergency resolution, with this endeavor and with their written Articles of Association, the settlers of Watauga drafted the inaugural constitution of civil government west of the Alleghanies, and formed what some have called the “first free and independent government in American.”

The text of the Articles of Association did not survive, but other documents, such as the Association’s later petition for annexation by North Carolina in 1776, provide insight into the operation of this self-government.  A magistrate’s court was formed with the consent of the people and was manned by five judges.  This body executed, by majority, judicial and legislative functions and carried out public business and land affairs. They adopted the laws of Virginia as the basis for their rulings. Read more at http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33636_Intro.pdf
</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Sycamore Shoals (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1775-1782</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Watauga Association</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Record Group 50: Early Land Records</dc:source>
<dc:type>IMAGE</dc:type>
<dc:relation>RG 50</dc:relation>
<dc:description>With the Watauga Purchase on March 19, 1775, the Watauga Association arranged with the Cherokee chiefs to secure the land along the Watauga, Holston, and Great Conaway Rivers. This negotiation solidified the hold the settlers had on the area and further legitimized their burgeoning experiment in democracy and self-government.  This volume containing the treaty and recording the Watauga Purchase grants provides the earliest record of the Watauga settlement and proves to be the first land grant book created for the area which became Tennessee. The original ledger book kept by Trustee Charles Robertson was used to record the grants. James Smith served as Clerk for the Land Office opening in Watauga on April 1, 1775; the office was probably located at the residence of John Carter. This volume was transferred to Jonesborough with the formation of Washington County and used to record Washington County grants issued by the State of North Carolina.  The presence of a “copied by” notation in TSLA’s volume and its designation as “Old Book A” indicate that this book is most likely a copy of the original and that the original resides in the old land office papers held at the Archives in Raleigh, North Carolina. The volume housed at TSLA was furnished by Washington County for the Tennessee Historical Society exhibit at the Tennessee Centennial Exposition in 1897. The book remained with the Tennessee Historical Society, eventually coming into the custody of the Tennessee State Library and Archives.  Read more at http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33636_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33636</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Treaties</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Watauga Association; Indians of North America; Cherokee Indians; Land grants -- Tennessee</dc:subject>
<dc:relation>Land Grants, Reel 24</dc:relation>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/101</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/111</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>An Act for the Enumeration of the Inhabitants of the Territory of the United States of America South of the River Ohio</dc:title>
<dc:description>This document is a nine page, unnumbered handwritten document found in &quot;Acts of the Southwest Territory.&quot; It is dated July 11, 1795, and signed by Governor William Blount and Joseph Hardin.  On May 26, 1790, President George Washington signed into law an act of Congress passed earlier in the month that established the Territory of the United States South of the River Ohio (Southwest Territory). Embracing the western lands ceded by the state of North Carolina on December 22, 1789, the new territory was to be governed under the terms of the Ordinance of 1787, which created its predecessor, the Northwest Territory. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33668_Intro.pdf
</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Knoxville (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1795 July 11</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Territory of the United States, South of the River Ohio. General Assembly</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Tennessee. General Assembly. Acts, Public and Private, 1790-[ongoing]</dc:source>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>RG 260</dc:relation>
<dc:description>On May 26, 1790, President George Washington signed into law an act of Congress passed earlier in the month that established the Territory of the United States South of the River Ohio (Southwest Territory). Embracing the western lands ceded by the state of North Carolina on December 22, 1789, the new territory was to be governed under the terms of the Ordinance of 1787, which created its predecessor, the Northwest Territory. This act, passed at the second session of the Southwest Territory General Assembly on July 11, 1795, called for the enumeration of all white male citizens in the territory. On November 28, 1795, the collected census reports from all eleven counties indicated that there were 77,262 inhabitants in the Southwest Territory, a total comfortably exceeding the minimum required for statehood (60,000). http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33668_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33668</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Census; Sheriffs; Oaths; Statehood</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Blount, William, 1749-1800; Hardin, Joseph, 1734-1801</dc:subject>
<dc:relation>RG 260</dc:relation>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/111</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/135</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>Constitution of Cherokee Nation, 1827</dc:title>
<dc:description>23 pages handwritten in ink that comprise the Cherokee Constitution of 1827. This early copy may have been written by Sam Houston. It was found in the 1827 Tennessee legislative papers and may have been given to the State of Tennessee in exchange for copies of Tennessee documents.  The Cherokee Constitution of 1827 represents a milestone in modern Cherokee history.  The document was a continuation of Cherokee attempts to establish their nation as a sovereign entity.  Beginning in the early 1820s, with the completion of Sequoyah’s Cherokee Syllabary, almost total literacy was achieved among the Cherokees.  In 1822, a Cherokee Supreme Court was formed and the first written laws of the Western Cherokees were laid down two years later.  In 1825, New Echota, Georgia, became the authorized capital of the Cherokees.  With this background-a literate population, written laws, a Supreme Court, and a nation’s capital-the Cherokees were seemingly on the road to secure for themselves a permanent place within the boundaries of their southeastern homelands.  Through the language of the constitution, it was hoped that Americans would no longer view Cherokees as “savages” but “civilized” individuals capable of governing themselves without being policed by the United States government.  However, ultimate expulsion from their lands occurred only ten years after the adoption of the Cherokee Constitution.
</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>New Echota (Ga.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1827 July 24</dc:date>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>1452</dc:relation>
<dc:description>A product of a convention held in early July 1827 at New Echota, Georgia, the constitution appears to be a version of the American Constitution adapted to suit Cherokee needs. Formulated mainly by the convention’s president, John Ross (1790-1866), the constitution does not represent a position of assimilation to white society but, rather, a conscious strategy to resist removal and maintain autonomy. Nevertheless, opposition to the constitution within the Cherokee nation was fierce. Traditionalists had long been concerned with laws passed by the Cherokee National Committee and Council that seemingly undermined old customs. To this faction, the Cherokee constitution seemed to be one more concession to white, Christian authority. Further opposition came in the form of vehement protests from state governments such as Georgia who insisted the document was an unconstitutional infringement on the state’s sovereign prerogatives regarding rule over Indian domains. For their part, John Ross and his followers saw the constitution as an attempt to maintain Cherokee autonomy in the midst of continued pressure from governments to remove the Cherokee from their homelands. An explanation of the political ramifications of the Cherokee Constitution of 1827 can be found in William G. McLoughlin, Cherokee Renascence in the New Republic (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1986), chapter 19. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33638_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33638</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Constitutions</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Cherokee Indians; Cherokee Nation Constitution (1827); Cherokee Indians -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Ross, John, 1790-1866</dc:subject>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/135</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/140</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>Tennessee Civil and Military Commission Book, Volume 1</dc:title>
<dc:description>This bound volume maintained by the Secretary of State represents the chronological recording of civil and military commissions issued by the Governor of Tennessee, John Sevier, from the beginning of statehood in 1796 to 1801.  The front section of the book includes those commissions that primarily reflect positions of state authority and is followed by commissions divided by county. The entries include the name of the individual, their commissioned position, and the date issued. The volume has no name.  
 The commission system that is represented by this volume recognizes individuals in the state who have been entrusted by the Governor with positions of military and civil authority. Appointments made by the state’s first governor John Sevier proved key as the former Territory of the United States of America South of the River Ohio adjusted to statehood and strove for stability. The positions that are recorded in this earliest volume are those that support the institutions of representative government, provide military security, and maintain order and structure within the fledgling state. Read more at http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33663_Intro.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Knoxville (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1796 April 2 - 1801 June 2</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Tennessee. Secretary of State</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Tennessee Civil and Military Commissions, 1796-1976</dc:source>
<dc:type>StillImage</dc:type>
<dc:relation>RG 195</dc:relation>
<dc:description>Centralized civil and military institutions that provided the foundations of security, liberty, public order, and social control in counties as Tennessee made the transition from frontier territory to more civilized statehood are represented by the recording of those names of civil and military authorities recognized and legitimized by the Governor in this founding commission volume. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33663_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33663</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Government officials; Governors; Judges; Sheriffs</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865; Appointments, Military -- Tennessee; Tennessee. Militia -- History; Tennessee -- History -- To 1865;  Coroners; Justices of the peace; Sevier, John, 1745-1815</dc:subject>
<dc:relation>RG 195</dc:relation>
<dc:relation>http://www.tennessee.gov/tsla/history/state/recordgroups/findingaids/rg195.pdf</dc:relation>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/140</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/141</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/142</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/143</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/144</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/145</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/146</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/147</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/148</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/149</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-02</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/188</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>Cumberland Compact</dc:title>
<dc:description>Original manuscript of the Cumberland Compact of Government, or Articles of Agreement, entered into by settlers on the Cumberland River, May 1, 1780, at what is now Nashville, and signed May 13, 1780 by 255 inhabitants of five stations on the river. First page missing; some following pages damaged, some quite significantly.  Handwritten in ink on paper.  One of the most important documents pertaining to the early history of the state of Tennessee is the Cumberland Compact. Richard Henderson, the representative for North Carolina on the western Virginia/North Carolina survey team, drew up the Cumberland Compact in May 1780 along with 250 other signatories. The Cumberland Compact called for a representative form of civil government by which the basis for courts, governance, and taxation were established. Each of the seven stations, or forts, of the Cumberland settlement was allowed a certain number of elected representatives to form a “Tribunal of Notables,” which included a total of twelve men. No voting qualifications were specified, but the Compact was open to all free white men who were willing to sign. This tribunal settled land claims and regulated the land office, in addition to receiving and dispersing funds and acting as a judicial body. 
At the same time, and perhaps more important, the document also created a favorable legal setting for Richard Henderson’s business in land speculation. In fact, only a small part of the document was devoted to governance; it was in large measure a contract dictating a legal framework for land transfers. Although Henderson did not remain in Tennessee like many of the other signatories, the document created a legal means for land transactions to occur, including the transfer of land from Native Americans to the early settlers. By 1784, about one third of the men who had signed the compact had been killed in battles with Native Americans. Additionally, many of their forts had been destroyed during Native American attacks. Despite these setbacks, the Cumberland Compact still represents one of the earliest declarations of self-governance for the state of Tennesseee.</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Nashville (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1780 May 1</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Henderson, Richard, 1735-1785</dc:creator>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>THS 155</dc:relation>
<dc:description>The Cumberland Compact was drawn up in May of 1780 by Richard Henderson, a land speculator and representative for North Carolina on the western Virginia/North Carolina survey team. The contract was signed in “Nashborough,” Tennessee, by 250 men of the new Cumberland settlement and established early government institutions (the infrastructure of courts, governance, and taxation) for the first settlers of the Tennessee territory. The Compact called for the creation of a civil government, and represented the settlers’ desire for self-governance and independence from North Carolina. Yet only a small part of the document was devoted to governance; it was in large measure a contract dictating a legal framework for land transfers. For instance, it dictated the legal grounds by which title to Native American land would be transferred to the new settlers, some of whom were land speculators. A complete transcription of the Cumberland Compact is available in A. W. Putnam's book, History of Middle Tennesseee; or, Life and Times of General James Robertson (Nashville, Tennessee, 1859). Included in this transcription is a complete list of all signatories. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33634_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee Historical Society</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33634</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Documents; Law &amp; legal affairs</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Tennessee -- History -- To 1865</dc:subject>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/188</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/191</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>Governor Sevier's Address to the first General Assembly</dc:title>
<dc:description>Governor John Sevier's address to the first General Assembly as transcribed by Daniel Smith.  Provides a more detailed account of the proceedings related to Tennessee's admission to the Union. Also directs the General Assembly to focus its first session on implementing the amended Act of Admission passed by Congress.</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Knoxville (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1796 July 30</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Smith, Daniel, 1748-1818</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Governor John Sevier Papers, 1796-1801</dc:source>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>GP 2</dc:relation>
<dc:description>Often called the &quot;Father of Tennessee, John Sevier was born in Virginia in 1745, he eventually moved to Washington County, TN and became Tennessee's first governor. He became a hero after he led an army of settlers at the Battle of Kings Mountain.</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33678</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Politics &amp; government</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Sevier, John, 1745-1815;Tennessee. General Assembly; Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</dc:subject>
<dc:relation>GP 2</dc:relation>
<dc:relation>http://www.tennessee.gov/tsla/history/govpapers/findingaids/gp2.pdf</dc:relation>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/191</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/192</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-08</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/193</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-08</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/194</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-04</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/199</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>An Ordinance for Circumscribing the Counties of Greene and Hawkins and Laying out Two New Counties</dc:title>
<dc:description>&quot;An Ordinance for Circumscribing the Counties of Greene and Hawkins and Laying Out Two New Counties&quot; is the first resolution appearing in the bound collection of acts passed by the Southwest Territory. The act is written in script and is four pages long.  The act gives specific boundary lines of the two new counties. The resolution was passed at Knoxville on June 11, 1792. It is signed by Governor William Blount and the territorial secretary, Daniel Smith.  On May 26, 1790, President George Washington signed into law an act of Congress passed earlier in the month that established the Territory of the United States South of the River Ohio (Southwest Territory). Embracing the western lands ceded by the state of North Carolina on December 22, 1789, the new territory was to be governed under the terms of the Ordinance of 1787, which created its predecessor, the Northwest Territory.
	The extent of the new territory was well defined. Containing about 43,000 square miles of land, it was restricted to North Carolina’s western district bounded on the north by the boundary of North Carolina and Virginia; on the west by a line in the middle of the Mississippi River, on the south by the parallel 35 degrees north and on the east by a jagged line running from the northeast to southwest connecting some dominant mountain peaks. It was this territory that in 1796 would become the state of Tennessee.
Read more http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33665_Intro.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Knoxville (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1792 June 11</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Territory of the United States, South of the River Ohio. General Assembly</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Tennessee. General Assembly. Acts, Public and Private, 1790-[ongoing]</dc:source>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>RG 260</dc:relation>
<dc:description>On May 26, 1790, President George Washington signed into law an act of Congress passed earlier in the month that established the Territory of the United States South of the River Ohio (Southwest Territory). Embracing the western lands ceded by the state of North Carolina on December 22, 1789, the new territory was to be governed under the terms of the Ordinance of 1787, which created its predecessor, the Northwest Territory.  The acts passed by the elected General Assembly were varied, reflecting the interests of the territorial lawmakers. It was felt by the Governor and his representatives that statehood would become more likely with the creation of counties and towns. The act creating the counties of Greene and Hawkins County was approved on November 20, 1792. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33665_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33665</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Boundaries; Physical geographic features; Politics &amp; government; Treaties; Legislative bodies; Resolutions</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Blount, William, 1749-1800; Greene County (Tenn.); Hawkins County (Tenn.); Nolichucky River (N.C. and Tenn.); Holston River, South Fork (N.C. and Tenn.); Tennessee River; Jefferson County (Tenn.); Smith, Daniel, 1748-1818</dc:subject>
<dc:relation>RG 260</dc:relation>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/199</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/200</identifier><datestamp>2014-03-26</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/201</identifier><datestamp>2014-03-26</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/202</identifier><datestamp>2014-03-13</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/225</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>Declaration of Rights; also, the constitution or form of government; State of Frankland</dc:title>
<dc:description>This constitution is the &quot;Houston Constitution,&quot; rejected by Franklin's Second Constitutional Convention of 1785 in Greeneville.  Constitutional committee member and major contributor Rev. Samuel Houston had these pamphlets printed to argue the merits of the rejected document in the preface.  Still infused with the spirit of the American Revolution and with an appetite already whetted by forays into self-government, the inhabitants of North Carolina’s trans-Appalachian counties of Washington, Sullivan, and Greene jumped at the opportunity that North Carolina’s cession of its western lands presented.  The state of North Carolina faced financial distress and carried the burden of war debt.  The challenges of governing its distant western settlements proved a strain.  The legislature of North Carolina orchestrated the “Great Land Grab of 1783,” allowing many of its members and major land speculators to obtain title to the best lands in the area.  Thus, it seemed advantageous to cede its western lands to Congress in 1784, with the provision that the titles remain valid.

Western residents of the Holston-Watauga region met in that same year at Jonesborough and unanimously confirmed their interest in forming an independent state.  When they met again in Jonesborough in December of 1784, they drafted a temporary, provisional constitution for the newly-formed State of Franklin, named in honor of Benjamin Franklin.  Unbeknownst to them, a month earlier North Carolina had repealed its Cession Act.  http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33664_Intro.pdf 
</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Greeneville (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1786</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Franklin (State). Constitutional Convention (1785)</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Tennessee Historical Society Miscellaneous Files, 1688-1951</dc:source>
<dc:type>IMAGE</dc:type>
<dc:relation>THS 191</dc:relation>
<dc:description>The proposed “Houston Constitution” represented here fits into the progression of constitutional considerations which faced the Franklinites as their young state developed and as they continued deliberations on adopting a “form of government.” The dissension caused by this process eroded support for the State of Franklin and contributed to its demise.  The meeting of western residents at Jonesborough in August of 1784 set things into motion. With the decision to opt for independent statehood came the election of delegates to a December 1784 convention set to draft a constitution. A provisional constitution based on North Carolina’s Constitution of 1776 was adopted as a temporary outline of government. Some minor changes were made to the North Carolina model, such as abolishing or reducing property requirements for holding an elected position. This Jonesborough Constitution contained a bill of rights as well, but, most notably, it was prefaced with a declaration of independence. This section aired the grievances of the western inhabitants and provided their justifications for seeking statehood.  This Jonesborough Constitution was lost to history until 1904. At that time, a copy was located in the office of the Insurance Commissioner in the capitol building at Raleigh, North Carolina. It was printed in the Charlotte Daily Observer on September 25, 1904 and appeared in the October 1904 issue of The American Historical Magazine. Samuel Cole Williams also included a copy of this Constitution in the appendix to his History of the Lost State of Franklin. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33664_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee Historical Society</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33664</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Constitutions</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Franklin (State); Franklin (State). Constitutional Convention (1785); North Carolina. General Assembly; State governments; Sevier, John,  1745-1815; Statehood (American politics)</dc:subject>
<dc:relation>678</dc:relation>
<dc:publisher>Bailey, Francis, 1735?-1815</dc:publisher>
<dc:rights>While TSLA houses an item, it does not necessarily hold the copyright on the item, nor may it be able to determine if the item is still protected under current copyright law. Users are solely responsible for determining the existence of such instances and for obtaining any other permissions and paying associated fees that may be necessary for the intended use.</dc:rights>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/225</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/253</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>1870 Constitution</dc:title>
<dc:date>1870</dc:date>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:description>Tennessee’s Constitution of 1870 was ratified in the wake of the Civil War and codified basic changes from that defining event in American history. The constitution remained essentially unchanged until 1953 and became in due course “the nation’s oldest unamended state constitution.” It is still the fundamental charter for the State of Tennessee. The most profound change in the 1870 Constitution was the permanent abolition of slavery in Tennessee. The real purpose of the Constitution’s framers, however, was to undo the electoral laws and other measures passed by Reconstruction governor William G. Brownlow. Conservative Democrats—many of them ex-Confederates—dominated the constitutional convention, and they were determined to prevent any future heavy-handed governorship such as Brownlow’s Radical regime. Delegates were driven by fear of an arbitrary executive and sought a Constitution that would guard against such abuses and excesses of state government from recurring. Many delegates had been disenfranchised by Brownlow and some imprisoned, and they were committed to restoring universal male suffrage. There was a good deal of argument over black men voting. With the passage of the 15th Amendment to the US Constitution (even though Tennessee voted NOT to ratify), convention delegates knew they could not repeal suffrage for African Americans. A Radical US Congress was watching for just such a misstep by former Confederate states. Instead, the convention authorized a poll tax in the Constitution as a tool for controlling who voted. To prevent the evils of Brownlowism from returning to the state, the convention enshrined in the Constitution certain restrictions on the governor’s power, namely, that he: 1.	Could not suspend habeas corpus 2.	Could not call out the militia without consent of the legislature 3.	Could not appoint local judges and county officials 4.	Had only limited veto power, which could be overridden by a simple majority of the General Assembly  The 1870 Constitution also put limits on the legislature’s ability to meet in marathon sessions, to enact omnibus bills, and to saddle the state with large debts. In a constitutional addendum, all of Brownlow’s judicial and county office appointments were vacated, effectively clearing out many Union loyalists appointed during Reconstruction. Such measures proved popular in a state devastated by war and weary of the turmoil of Radical Reconstruction. The new Constitution was approved in a statewide referendum by a vote of 98,128 to 33,872.</dc:description>
<dc:identifier>39417</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Constitutions; Documents</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Constitutions; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877)</dc:subject>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/253</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/254</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/255</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/256</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/257</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/258</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/259</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/260</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/261</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header status="deleted"><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/262</identifier><datestamp>2014-04-03</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/265</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>An Act for the admission of the State of Tennessee into the Union</dc:title>
<dc:description>Reprint of a Federal Statute (Chapter XLVII) from the published Acts of Congress, entitled An Act for the admission of the State of Tennessee into the Union. Approved June 1, 1796.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1845</dc:date>
<dc:creator>United States</dc:creator>
<dc:identifier>33675</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Politics &amp; government</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1775-1865</dc:subject>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/265</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/272</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>An Act to Cut and Clear a Waggon Road to the Settlements on the Cumberland River in the Mero District</dc:title>
<dc:description>The document is a six page, unnumbered handwritten document found in the &quot;Acts of the Southwest Territory.&quot; It is dated September 27, 1794 and signed by Governor William Blount and Secretary David Wilson.  On May 26, 1790, President George Washington signed into law an act of Congress passed earlier in the month that established the Territory of the United States South of the River Ohio (Southwest Territory). Embracing the western lands ceded by the state of North Carolina on December 22, 1789, the new territory was to be governed under the terms of the Ordinance of 1787, which created its predecessor, the Northwest Territory.
	The extent of the new territory was well defined. Containing about 43,000 square miles of land, it was restricted to North Carolina’s western district bounded on the north by the boundary of North Carolina and Virginia; on the west by a line in the middle of the Mississippi River, on the south by the parallel 35 degrees north and on the east by a jagged line running from the northeast to southwest connecting some dominant mountain peaks. It was this territory that in 1796 would become the state of Tennessee.
	The new territory had two centers of population approximately 150 miles apart, separated by the Cumberland Mountains. The larger population, some 28,000, was in the eastern part of the territory in a corridor from 25 to 60 miles wide that extended from the Virginia line down the Holston River Valley about 110 miles to the southwest. Settlements were clustered along the Holston, Watauga, Nolichucky, French Broad and Little Rivers and their tributaries. The smaller Cumberland settlements of approximately 7,000 were located along an 80 mile stretch of the Cumberland River from Bledsoe’s Lick in the east to Clarksville in the west. The Indians regarded settlements in the Cumberland area and in certain parts of the Holston Valley as encroachments on their territory.
http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33666_Intro.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Knoxville (Tenn.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1794 September 27</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Territory of the United States, South of the River Ohio. General Assembly</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Tennessee. General Assembly. Acts, Public and Private, 1790-[ongoing]</dc:source>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>RG 260</dc:relation>
<dc:description>On May 26, 1790, President George Washington signed into law an act of Congress passed earlier in the month that established the Territory of the United States South of the River Ohio (Southwest Territory). Embracing the western lands ceded by the state of North Carolina on December 22, 1789, the new territory was to be governed under the terms of the Ordinance of 1787, which created its predecessor, the Northwest Territory. It was believed that road building was essential for the territory in order to gain statehood. This act, passed September 27, 1794, created a lottery to pay for a wagon road from the Southwest Point to the settlements on the Cumberland River in the Mero District. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33666_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee State Library &amp; Archives</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33666</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Lotteries; Trails &amp; paths; Roads; Dirt roads; Road cuts</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Blount, William, 1749-1800; Cumberland River (Ky. and Tenn.); Winchester, James, 1752-1826; Donelson, Stockley, d. ca. 1804; Cocke, William, 1747-1828; Cherokee Indians</dc:subject>
<dc:relation>RG 260</dc:relation>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/272</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/281</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>1818 Letter from Cherokee chiefs to Gov. McMinn</dc:title>
<dc:description>Seven handwritten pages, in ink, of a letter from various Cherokee leaders to Tennessee Governor Joseph McMinn discussing the removal of Cherokees west of the Mississippi.  Notation at top: &quot;For the Raleigh Register.&quot; At end of letter: &quot;A True Copy attest; John Ross member of the Nation'l Committee.&quot; The 1818 letter from the Cherokee chiefs to Gov. McMinn, in effect, stated it would be against the best interests of the Cherokees to compel a whole nation of people, contrary to their free will and choice, to leave the land of their nativity.  Furthermore, Cherokee leadership flatly rejected your propositions for an entire extinguishment of all our claims to lands east of the Mississippi river.  The letter of 1818 represents the Cherokees determination, albeit futile, to remain a free and distinct nation rather than acquiesce to the unfair demands of the United States government.  A printed copy of the letter, including the names of those Cherokee leaders and warriors who signed it can be found in the American State Papers, Indian Affairs, II: 486-487.</dc:description>
<dc:date>1818</dc:date>
<dc:source>Tennessee Historical Society Miscellaneous Files, 1688-1951</dc:source>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>THS 191</dc:relation>
<dc:description>This letter, written and signed by over forty chiefs and warriors of the Cherokee National Council, is addressed to Tennessee Governor Joseph McMinn and dated November 21, 1818. McMinn, under pressure from the United States government and land-hungry speculators, found himself in the position of trying to coerce the Cherokees to relinquish their lands and remove to lands west of the Mississippi. Specifically, the letter is a reaction to the stipulations of the Treaty of 1817 which presented the eastern Cherokee with two options: removal or citizenship. Those Cherokees who decided to move to Arkansas would be provided with tracts of land similar to what they left behind; while those who decided to stay would have to become American citizens and be confined within reservations of 640 acres per each head of household. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33637_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee Historical Society</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33637</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Correspondence; Contracts; Treaties</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Cherokee Indians -- Relocation; Cherokee Indians -- Treaties; McMinn, Joseph, 1758-1824</dc:subject>
<dc:relation>678</dc:relation>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/281</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record><record><header><identifier>oai:cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org:tfd/303</identifier><datestamp>2015-03-19</datestamp><setSpec>tfd</setSpec></header>
<metadata>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
<dc:title>King George III's Proclamation of 1763</dc:title>
<dc:description>The first in a bound collection of colonial documents is a complete copy of the Proclamation of 1763 promulgated at the end of the French and Indian War by King George III of Great Britain. The item is hand-written in ink on paper, copied by John Milton, Georgia Secretary of State.  
 Issued by the British Crown at the end of the French &amp; Indian War, the Proclamation of 1763 laid out the system of governing the North American interior which had been won from France and decreed that the Indians and their land would be treated with respect. It is one of the first colonial documents that pertained to the area that would become Tennessee. In it George III pronounces his intention to reward soldiers in the recent war with bounty land obtained by consent from the natives-a novel concept that henceforth would be the model for distributing western lands. More importantly for the settlement of Tennessee, the king forbade his colonial subjects to move west beyond the crest of the Appalachians and trespass on Indian land. This edict was promptly ignored by frontiersmen who began to move into what is now East Tennessee, sowing seeds of resentment towards the Crown that would flower into open rebellion during the Revolution. The Proclamation of 1763 actually marks the beginning of forays by hunters into the Tennessee country, soon to be followed by the migration of backcountry families onto transmontane lands claimed by natives. The early history of Tennessee prior to American independence can be seen as a sustained effort by pioneer settlers to thwart and circumvent the provisions of this proclamation, much to the detriment of Tennessee’s native people.</dc:description>
<dc:coverage>Savannah (Ga.)</dc:coverage>
<dc:date>1795</dc:date>
<dc:creator>Milton, John, ca. 1740-1804</dc:creator>
<dc:source>Milton, John, Manuscript Copybook of Early Georgia Documents, 1795</dc:source>
<dc:type>Text</dc:type>
<dc:relation>THS 024</dc:relation>
<dc:description>This 1795 copy of King George III’s proclamation at the close of the French &amp; Indian War (aka Seven Year’s War) is one of the earliest and most significant documents for the history of Tennessee. The copy was produced by Georgia’s first Secretary of state, John Milton, and was found among the papers of John Sevier (Tennessee’s first governor and one of the chief violators of the edict). Promulgated after the 1763 Treaty of Paris, the proclamation lays out the British Crown’s regulations for the governance of its new territories in North America. Specifically, the king introduces the bounty land warrant system as a method of paying soldiers of the war, a method of public land disposal that was adopted by the colonies (later states) of North Carolina and Virginia and greatly impacted the distribution of Tennessee land. George III also proclaims a desire to protect the native inhabitants of America by prohibiting his American subjects from migrating and settling across the crest of the Appalachian mountains. The prohibition had little effect in stemming the tide of American westward movement. http://www.tn.gov/tsla/founding_docs/33639_HistNote.pdf</dc:description>
<dc:source>Tennessee Historical Society</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>33639</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>Documents; Law &amp; legal affairs</dc:subject>
<dc:format>Image/jp2</dc:format>
<dc:subject>Tennessee -- History -- To 1865</dc:subject>
<dc:identifier>http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/tfd/id/303</dc:identifier></oai_dc:dc>
</metadata>
</record>
</repository>
